so
um
who can tell me
what is samadhi
establishment of the mind um
um
okay can you describe that
what is establishment of the mind um
seeing the sign of the mind
that's one way to describe it so um any description will be
will be
a thought or an image
yeah it's always the mind always
precedes any description that you you can give
any description that you you can give
um so yeah but still like
somebody comes to the booth and wants to
learn some what is someone yeah yeah
just you can just stick to samad you
have to describe the mind and the sign
and what's behind
just what is samadhi and we translate it
as composure
so can you describe what what is
composure to somebody that doesn't
really know what to look for
so
give me just practical even mundane
examples of what is composure
instead of
getting drawn into the content of
thoughts or images
one sees
those thoughts or images as thoughts
thoughts or images as thoughts
so one becomes established on the nature
of one's experience okay
but before we get talking about that
level can anybody give me a
mundane example of composure because
people do experience say somebody who
doesn't practice a dharma
would experience throughout the life
forms of composure
so what is that composure just give me
some examples of it
not being bothered or moved or disturbed
by
disturbing events let's say your
particular particular
circumstances that arise
you can not be
shaken by them so like for example if
somebody is in a good mood
for whatever reason
[Music] they go throughout the day in a good
they go throughout the day in a good
mood and even bad things or bad people
don't necessarily affect them
so so it's not the reason why i'm coming
on to this is because it's not just the
composure of an idea
it also it is partially yes but that
idea implies emotional composure is a
background of it so
so
yeah mood would be an example equally
someone's mind can be composed upon a
not so good mood
which means even good things would annoy
them and irritate them yes so they're
kind of
anything that happens comes within that
sort of
bad mood so everything is has a kind of
a
disagreeable baseline i suppose or an agreeable
baseline i suppose or an agreeable
baseline if they're in a good mood so
composure then does a person have a say
then does a person have a say
in
in the mood really
really
i would say yes
really so if you say no why why is it no i
so if you say no why why is it no i
think there's no personal um
you can't change it
it
presents it's of you of its own that's
yeah that's true on that level and you
say yes why is that
because it is possible like even uh
it is possible like even uh
in mundane terms um
like my father would say no i can
you know i can
put myself i can put myself in a good
mood by
um
thinking about certain uh things made
remember reminding myself of how
i suppose um
fortunate i am and compared to other
people so you know i can i can keep my
mood not from going too bad or too good
by doing certain things and by
reflecting a certain way and actually
yeah both are right
so
what you were referring to is the aspect
of yeah mind is on its own
moods of the mind
are phenomenon on its own
however your actions and as in are you
allowing the unrestrained wild animal
mind to go where it wants moods will get
worse moods will get depressed moods will get
moods will get depressed moods will get
like agitated
or along those lines or are you making
the effort to restrain it moods will get
lighter and better
so
you don't have a say in the phenomenon
of the mood but you do actually have to
say whether you're indirectly feeding it
or not
and that's that that recognition and
exactly like you know that's what i said
the one who doesn't live a celibate life
i a householder in the suttas if he
frequently recollects the buddha the
dhamma the sangha the virtue
he will get pleasant abiding of a type
of samadhi here and now
so the mind will be composed upon this
frequent reflection upon certain values
even when you don't feel like thinking
about those things you make the effort
to think about those things and make a
practice out of reflecting upon those
things day in day out
and those are factual composers of the
mind that they would have said are
pleasant abiding for the level of
somebody who is not a celibate
now of course if you want to have higher
pleasant bindings you need to restrain
more but the point is it comes down to
that frequently correction recollection
and reflection that is what will incline
the mind and it will say what what one
frequently thinks and ponders on that's
where the mind is going to go
so is it sensuality or non-sensuality is
it irritation fall finding ill will or
non irritation not for fine not your
will and that's that background practice
and that's that background practice
that that reflect reflection
so
how is then
composure frequent recollection
frequent recollection
different from
concentration
so concentration you do mean in terms of
like focusing practices i'm in
concentration okay let's let's say what
is concentration in the most mundane
terms how would you describe
concentration somebody says hey
somebody says hey
it is a kind of um you're
you're
at the expense of everything else you're
you're honing in on something particular
so
if i if i don't
have any experience in anything
and i come and ask you i heard this word
concentration how do i do that what is concentration
how do i do that what is concentration
so how would you just advise me in most
mundane terms
just pick an object and focus on it
pick an object and focus on it
attend to it closely or yeah essential
object that would involve it could be as
that would involve it could be as
mundane as like um
yeah just main examples of concentration
um trying to play the piano being very
focused on
having something that is
totally absorbing all of your attention
in the sense of i have to focus on this
thing and if i
and if i
um forget it for a second i'm going to
make a mistake in my piano playing so i
can't do that so it comes down to
attention to detail the particular thing
that's in front of you
so how is that
or is that attention to particular
object of your senses or even idea for
that matter
is that different
from recollection that we just talked
about the composure
yes how
because it depends upon that object
it depends on that object that your mind
is
focused on what depends on the object the
on what depends on the object the
concentration concentration
concentration where is the dependence because you
where is the dependence because you
could
say i don't care what i'm concentrated
on i practice concentration of
everything like anything that comes into
my field of attention
i attend to it okay okay i see what you
mean um
it depends on that object basically
staying the same and not going away
because if you're sort of i concentrate
on anything that comes into my field of
attention then you wouldn't call that
really concentration because it would be
diverse like it would be any type of
objects that
but that's that's my point does it
matter what object it is in order to
define a concentration so it's what you
do exactly it's how you uh so so then
you could
concentrate on many different objects
that come your way and still practice
concentration even if they're different
objects yes
so then uh
so how's that different or is that
different or why is that different
because like um
if we say
recollecting the certain themes
frequently dwelling on them can you
concentrate on them is that is that what
we are saying can that be there
so what's the difference then if you're
concentrating
that one's concentrating one is
attending a thing whereas recollection
as i understand is more about discerning
so to say or seeing the background but
so seeing in like mundane terms you
could say one of the most obvious
differences is
when you're concentrating you are doing
it
you are attending what's there
but when you're recollecting
there is already a certain
degree of space for the lack of better word
of space for the lack of better word
between you and your mind because see
you are not trying to focus on something
and concentrate and attend to something
particular you're actually providing the
broader context for where your mind
already is so that on its own will
incline in that direction yeah it's
indirect yeah yeah exactly so it's
you you set up as you would have said
you know like
the water comes down the mountain and it
starts filling the pores and so imagine
now you're just you can't stop that
water or you can't i mean you can try but the
or you can't i mean you can try but the
point is to direct it elsewhere
by by setting this context they will
then encourage it to go in that
direction oh yeah don't look there look here look
oh yeah don't look there look here look
at this and it's bad over there and all
this danger peril lack of satisfaction
and so on are the themes that if you
sustain the mind will turn away from it
and why can't you do that with
concentration
why can't you just concentrate on your
mind and make it go that way
because it's not an object that you can
exactly yeah people keep it comfortable
thinking the concentration is the mind
watching you don't see your mind when
you're concentrated with it
it's not a sense object it's always it's
always yeah before yeah exactly so in
the same sense i will
it's actually exactly the same if i were
to be looking at visual things
to see my eyes there
that is impossible
or feeling tactile sensations
to see my body there that is impossible
body is the background body is the organ
for your sensations so then so then
can
concentration be useful
in terms of practice
initially is a prerequisite for
reading the suitors getting information
getting data
in terms of well attending to right
things sure yeah
but i'm talking about
i'm talking about
practice
of concentration in itself
can it be beneficial
yes if the mind is inclining towards a
house and things
it could be helpful to
intentionally direct it towards
direct it towards
more holes and things
but can you discern wholesome when
you're concentrated
is that a possibility
i mean some things are obviously
unwholesome yes yes but while being concentrated do
yes yes but while being concentrated do
you have the possibility of discerning
whether you are attending to something
wholesome or not
not by virtue of the concentration or if
you include but it would be at the
expense of the concentration yes
so then the question comes down to
recognizing that
degree or clarifying it where does
attention become concentration practice
like you you cannot but not attend
anything but you can certainly learn how not to
but you can certainly learn how not to
uh
overlook the background the context
the background the context
the meaning the intentionality behind
whatever you're attending currently
and that context is what tells you
because that's where your intentions are
that's what tells you whether this is
wholesome and i should allow it to be
attended further or unwholesome and i
should not welcome and not delight it
and make sure i don't attend as the
buddha said particular signs and
features that induce you of lust and
would increase the unwholesome state
but it doesn't say i'll just
focus on it harder
concentrate because see even if even if it's a good
because see even if even if it's a good
thing
say if it's a wholesome thing
if you actually think okay if i double
down now in attending to it i'll get
there faster you want to distract yourself
faster you want to distract yourself
further that's actually it always has to
be done yeah it always has to be done at
the expense of the context
at the expense of composure yes that's
what i meant it's um
so ironically the concentration practice
is directly opposite of samadhi practice
samadhi being the composer of the theme
of the context
recollecting things rightly that then
sustain and incline your mind in certain
ways concentration
basically means overshooting the mark
and abandoning the context even if it's
as i said concentrating upon the good
things
and that's why it's that the whole
practice is to learn how not to
overshoot or like undershoot in a sense
of ignore the whole thing of course yeah
attend to something but don't let it
become a focusing concentration object
in practice because you cannot possibly
do that and at the same time sustain the
background context of
your intentionality the meaning the mood
behind all of that
so then can anybody
elaborate or give some examples on
as we said composure equals
establishment of the mind
equals right recollections write themes
right context equals putting the work
there so can anybody give me a few examples of
so can anybody give me a few examples of
right composure and write recollection
a few practices let's say that
seeing the body as present
and seeing the body
always present whatever
one is doing how would you see that how
would you go about it so you say yeah
okay i want to see the body present what
do we do
by not
being too involved with
what one is doing
at any time what constitutes be too
involved what we just described like concentrate
what we just described like concentrate
on something in a sense
and not right so abstaining from
concentration yes would then that reveal
me the background not in itself
so back on to my original question then
how do i reveal that background
what do i do
well it could be just those basic things
like this so to say you know being um
aware of what you're doing not in the
sense of the
um
actual object of activity that you're doing but
object of activity that you're doing but
what your body is doing in the sense of
okay i'm sitting walking getting up but
just as a way
to
kind of indirectly notice the fact that
no matter where you do what you're where
you're going your body is
always there
but how do i prevent that
from becoming my
concentration object
it is it see that often does come like i
was doing it like that as in trying to
make it an object of okay i am so how do
i not do that how do i establish my mind
how do i
sustain and develop the right context
the right mood
to understand or
to understand that the body
the body that we are talking about now
cannot be seen as an object
yeah so how do you understand that
what do i do to get to that
understanding what would be the necessary
frequently uh reflect and ponder upon it
yeah and in order to frequently reflect and
and in order to frequently reflect and
ponder upon it what do i need
not forgetting the theme
where do i get the theme from
where to get details about the theme
i'm studying discourses
yeah so
you learn about the themes that
obviously counter your whole experience
you do want to the whole tendency is to
attend what's right in front of you i
mean that's the definition of
of like essentiality in general
like living
you're being existing on the level of
sense objects that's the measure of
what's real
so then whatever you attend to it you
make it an object by doing overly doing
so
ionizato let's put it that way
so then you learn about the right things
but you will still be making them
objects of your attention
but if you study if you hear if you make
sufficient effort to recollect and
rediscern and re-clarify
you will be learning how not to yeah
so in other words
in order for you to have the right
composure right establishment of the
mind you need to abandon all of your
wrong views that require certain degree
of attention so the degree of
concentration certain degrees of
assumption of of sense objects and so on
so you need the right view
so we're back on to what we always say
you can't get the right samadhi without
the right view because it's not a
technique it's not a method that will
have automatic result if you go through
certain steps
it's the right context the right
establishment the right mood the mood of
a neutral feeling that's not perturbed
by whole by uh sorry by pleasant or
unpleasant by agreeable or disagreeable so yeah
so yeah
you learn the themes by studying the
suitors and
and
again it won't it won't take that much
of a study to see that that's what it
was often talking about
to
incline your mind so it's wholesome take
it away from unwholesome how do you do
it well not by watching your belly
movements or soles of your feet you do
it by pondering on the danger
the peril the lack of satisfaction
uh the benefits all these all these
values that you actually have to keep
sustaining through your own active
thinking and reflection
and that's what first ghana becomes
active thinking and pondering
that is fully
withdrawn separated went beyond
the central domain
the domain where you assume the sense
objects to be the measure of your
being of what is
and see thinking and pondering clearly
for what it is so yeah
so yeah
you have to
really work make the effort be prepared
to make the effort to try and understand
what the suitors are genuinely talking
about or what you might hear somebody saying
or what you might hear somebody saying
that doesn't initially
it can't initially make perfect sense to
you you have to be prepared to
you have to be prepared to
question
your sort of
assumptions of what these things mean
you start from this position of
ignorance in the sense when you start reading
in the sense when you start reading
theater wrong view everything you that
everything is misunderstood everything
is like
or
and you yeah just
just
just to kind of see that that type of
attention is possible or that there is
another way of attending to things
that that there is a
a kind of a
a background a form of attention or
peripheral attention or whatever you
want to call it whatever word you might
say initially it won't make sense this
is basically learning how to
how to attend because now you start by
over attending everything
that's it or completely not attending
what you need just either ignoring or
overdoing the middle ground of it where attention
the middle ground of it where attention
is there without you losing the sight of
its context of its origin of its womb
jonasso that needs to be learned
that needs to be learned
that needs to be discerned first
sustained endured and then kind of
recognized for what it is and then yes
you can you can cultivate but even then
you won't become an object of your
cultivation in that
in that
concentration sense you know in the
broadest theoretical sense yeah it's a
phenomenon it can be a theme an object
that you think about it
it's an indirect way not directly
wanting to change what is in front of
you but changing its indirect way
changing the context and that will
automatically change yes yeah so you as i said you
change yes yeah so you as i said you
kind of
you you guide
you encourage your mind in certain to go
in certain directions
irrigators um directing the water
directing the water like you can't bring
the water to that
but you know it will go if you create
the pathway for it so
so
okay so now that we clarified that you
need to
know you need to abandon the wrong views
and wrong assumptions that revolve
around the nature of your own current
attention slash over attention
what are the examples of some mind
establishments upon the right context
the right composures
i will be like the most
basic basic example
the impermanence of phenomena
yeah but as a mood
that your mind is established upon as an
imperturbable mood
how would you that would be more closely
coming out of it
yeah but then you would go into anxiety
or despair
this might be how impermanence reveals
itself first
but that could also be seen as a mood
one can be in an anxious mood yeah of
course yeah which means then you become
better so how can you remain unprepared
so how can you remain unprepared
when the point comes for you to think
about impermanence anxiety cessation
how can the mind remain unperturbed
there is training before us
but it's trained beforehand so
uh
does does the restraint
and virtue
does that require
a certain context
a certain unifying idea not necessarily
not necessarily
how would you then know what to do
yes i mean at least from the beginning
yeah no i know the strategies i'm just
curious but even then it's not that blank again
but even then it's not that blank again
you wouldn't
you wouldn't even know what to do unless
there's some unifying idea of what what
restraint is so that is what defines
your behavior
what you referring to is that then in
return practicing that behavior
practicing that behavior
will then contribute further toward that
thing so
so
it can grow and develop simply through
uh sense restraint and not not breaking
the precips not doing things that are
contrary to the theme you took on and that is
to the theme you took on and that is
already from some other
and now you can
how do you um
how do you increase
let's say like that how do you cultivate
the samadhi of virtue the samadhi of
sense restraint is it by restraining
even harder
and saying no and creating even more
rules
what is it then if it's not that how
would you how would you cultivate
bring to fulfillment um
the the samadhi of virtue
if you're not creating more rules and
adding more observances to do
clarifying the danger of
cravings yeah so by frequently thinking
about while you're still doing the same
while you're still doing the same
restraint
and same uh virtue you're not adding
more things to say no to
but that doesn't mean oh okay so i'm
virtuous now i can stop thinking about
it no actually
yes you're virtuous yes your sense
restraint and now
often think about the danger of
non-virtue the peril of sensuality the peril of
the peril of sensuality the peril of
acting out of your will
and that's how you're cultivating it
further so you don't need to do externally
so you don't need to do externally
anything more in that sense
the benefits of that virtue the benefits
of virtue that comes from it yeah the
joy that you factually know comes from
it
when you when you're uh blameless
when virtue is unbroken
that might also take some time though in
terms of the virtue so some good reasons
or some
faith or confidence in the beginning
might also be a unifying factor for
sticking to the virtue exactly yeah
that's why basically all of those powers
that the buddha talks about
in the suttas they are all kind of
exactly that unifying factors there are
certain certain things that that enable
you to then cultivate the right context
and and and
in right practice really towards this
passion so the point is that you realize that
so the point is that you realize that
okay so
you keep the virtue
you're sense restrained
and now you wanna even a householder in
the suttas
who keeps the five precepts you know but
it's it's moderate it's careful
uh
watchful of his actions
so he now wants to practice ahmadi
and what did the buddha then say
okay then you sit watch your nostrils
feel your belly coming up and down
sensations move slowly concentrate no
move slowly concentrate no
he said what you do is then you
recollect further
of the same thing your order so your
samadhi practice is then on the level of
actively thinking about certain themes
certain benefits certain drawbacks
certain rewards certain dangers
certain values
and the mind will become composed as a
result of that practice that's obviously
directly standing upon your virtue that
is factually unbroken
yeah and that yeah but experiencing the joy
and that yeah but experiencing the joy
of that
recollecting your virtue and
experiencing the joy of that it's a it
does say the body becomes calm you know
the mind becomes happy
that is the composure leads to knowledge
and vision yeah exactly so the point is
that your body
your body
will become calm
and agreeable as a result of mind that
has been calmed and made agreeable as a
result of directing it in a certain
themes and moods basically based on
certain values behavior
values behavior
values and behaviors exactly
so practice of samadhi then is practice
of
right recollection
right thinking
right evaluation
all of that results in somatic and then
person who is factually and by the way
i'm talking about a lay person out like
just five precepts you don't even need
to be celibate but the rest of again you
you set
periods of day
where you just sit and think about
actually making your mind think about
these themes and values
not like well i'm i'm i keep the precept
so i can just do everything else within
that and i don't need to think about yes
yeah you can go about it but you won't
have samadhi
you want the samadhi you don't go to
concentrate you don't let your mind
completely wild you keep um
directing it and kind of re-enclosing it
in that right context
and the factual result would be that if
you spend say
a few days building that up
it will start to persist in your mind
those values those themes the thoughts
those states of mind
let's say
um something happens and then uh
somebody says something to you and you
get angry um you're like i'm not
practicing somebody anymore no i'm
getting angry then it's like um it's
like yeah so so then in that instance this
yeah so so then in that instance this
idea but i had this set the idea that
for three days i would reflect and think
and ponder only
i mean in that instance that then then
what is necessary is not to then impose
some kind of
um yeah
idea of me
practicing somebody in a vertex commas
but about to see
about to see
um yeah what has arisen by itself so so
you have no say in the fact that well i
think the first recognition should be
simply that if you got angry you didn't
you have somebody to begin with yeah
so
you and i you got
i get actively angry yeah if you just
got it well no i was going to say that
so if you establish if you have actually
been cultivating these themes and
and actively reflecting upon things that
would often say you should reflect upon
uh you wouldn't get us angry and you
would see the difference now because see
the mind went really quite some distance
in a good direction and it's there
and somebody from a bad direction comes
and tries to entice it yes you might
make it turn around and maybe start
walking but it's still quite far before
it's actually in the bad field
and you will see that
so now you will actually have confidence
and recognize okay so i don't need to
you know jump and choke that animal when
he gets and then fight it directly no
okay now i got a bit distracted let me
ignore this thing that's trying to take
my attention through centrality or anger
and instead
keep cultivating the same indirect
themes and cultivations and
encouragements and the further it goes
the harder it will be to get disturbed
on things that are now even more distant
so if you have spent few days thinking
about and something made you angry and
yes you got really angry the animal
means okay
i need to spend more time cultivating
the same stuff
yeah you see and each time you cultivate
it further through right reflection
right recollection right evaluation
and constantly think about those values
and re-evaluating and so on the mind is
traveling in a good direction further
inviting and further as long of course
as your virtue remains unbroken and
sense restraint uh protected
you kind of see
that you are mistaken in a way like
yeah you have to resist the urge to deal
with it yeah exactly head-on because
that would require abandoning the
context and absorbing yourself in it to
get rid of it the content yeah yeah
that's what i kept saying before most of
meditation practice that people do today
is rooted in a version
trying to get rid of the stuff that
bothers them antidoting this with that
with this with that with it no all of
that requires you to abandon the context
or not even have it to begin with
so that's how you then protect
your samadhi again for the lack of
better description you're protected by
recognizing where the importance is ah
it's on the level of
value value revalue
uh thinking about the danger and the
peril of of of losing those values
because how how quickly the mind will
then go back into you know states that
are not pleasant for me
uh remembering all the the uh like the
joy the lightness the clarity you got as
a result of established mood properly
where things that exactly used to make
you furious or lastful
haven't moved you now
now if you forget about your mind it
will start going back
unless of course it's fully has fully
uprooted those kills but so you realize okay so i
those kills but so you realize okay so i
don't need to fight things directly all
i need to do is virtue sense restraint
obviously solitude to that degree
and then
make a practice active practice of uh
thinking and reflecting and
re-evaluating these wholesome themes
these wholesome themes
and when they become dry and my mind
starts getting distracted that's where
my work is
not in finding something new to
concentrate and so on no it's just
finding ways to rekindle the same themes
until the mind has traveled far enough
that he cannot come back to these
unwholesome pastures
it's also quite different to be
doing all of those things that protects
the samadhi
out of the knowledge that you are
protecting your samadhi and that that is
what you're doing it for rather than
kind of just
doing them to do them yeah
and like out of that kind of knowledge
again i'm
protecting my composure protecting my
mind yeah that already see you wouldn't
be able to discern any of that unless
you're already seeing the signs of your
mind unless you're already seeing that
kind of
indirect relationship between you and
your own mind
it's not something you can directly
attend to have possessed control
so you recognize it okay so it's
basically like
yeah an animal that if you provide open
the gates it will go there if you close
those gates and start encouraging taking
it away sending it in the other way it
will go that way so it will incline to
whatever you're frequently thinking and
pondering about
as the suitors say
so that's your job to incline it in the
right direction
not to force it in you know shut the
shove the right direction down his
throat and
and
all these themes and reflections and
reevaluations can you do them by concentrating on them no no
impossible impossible
but can you do them if you completely
don't pay any attention to that theme
equally impossible
so that's the middle ground i'm talking
about
and factually back onto the blade person
who only keeps the five precepts but
recollects the dharma the themes of the
dharma the value of the virtue the
all of those and constantly is sort of
feeding and sustaining
those evaluations and re-evaluations in
their mind
uh yeah even within their late setting
that is crowded and dusty as the suitors
often say
things that
used to disturb them or
disagreeable people and events will not
be able
to move their mind and make them lose
perspective as much as they did before
and back onto the original example when
we started
imagine you're in a perpetually good
mood now you still recognize when a bad thing
now you still recognize when a bad thing
happens
but none of the things becomes bad
enough to uproot your good mood to
uproot your imperturbable mood
why because you have cultivated it
you've sustained it you've protected it
and you have invested active effort in
thinking pondering evaluating
re-evaluating about those things
so in other words you won't lose the
context even when things are not good as
the students say now if you
cultivate the right context
establish the right composure
the body will become calm
joyful the mind will become calm then
you can see and not act out of a version
even things that as i said are
disagreeable because you were calm beforehand on that
because you were calm beforehand on that
right level where the mind has been
withdrawn from unwholesome
then you won't be by default trying to
get rid of the discomfort
in other words you won't lose
perspective and then you will see it and
then you would see that yes exactly if i
were to engage with this and try to get
rid of it or if it's a agreeable thing
if i try to go for it i will lose the
comfort i will lose the composure thus i
will lose the comfort of pleasant
abiding here and now
so and that's that's what the samadhi
does in the suit is yes
calmness of the body
um contentment of the mind a happy mind
is content in mind the one that's happy
and contented can see things clearly as
it were to say
but it clearly says before that as well
how do you get to that contented mind
and happy mind and calm body and joyful
body through basically developing these
through basically developing these
themes
to the extent necessary
but see
people tend to ignore everything else in
between and try to get a method that
will calm the body make the mind happy
get them to see the reality
because they recognize that
what they're trying to skip so to say is
where the work is
i don't think they recognize
i think it's it's more like rooted in
just uh not knowing where the problem is
uh not knowing where the problem is
which is in you already
being on the level of sense objects
through overly attending everything and
that's the measure so now you hear about
the practice and you think the practice
is there concentrate on the right things
because you can even what i was going to
say is like what's interesting
i think yeah i remember times
before when
you through kind of
actually sort of accidentally in a way
or incidentally doing some of the right
things i would
i would
sort of come to
a relative degree of composure let's say
to some extent
but i wouldn't have recognized
that is something to protect and
cultivate further yeah exactly i
wouldn't have recognized that as
something to protect nor would i have
seen on what base it was really i would
have kind of
thought still thought that the important
thing was
some form of um
content concentration so by by kind of
not recognizing that
where the on what base this kind of
degree of composure was
i would just kind of uh yeah if i would
have stayed for a while and then
uh become lost or yeah because you
haven't actually
recognized back then you haven't seen
the mind
for what it is
so you overlooked it
it's there
it's not like it doesn't exist in people
that don't see it
they just don't know where to look they
don't know
to what degree
to look
so they always overlook or handle it so
it's like even if you are doing some of
the right things it's not recognizing
what things are the right things and
what things are the wrong thing and
that's exactly the definition of the
right view knowing important as
important and unimportant is unimportant
without a right view you will be
basically regarding unimportant things
as essential and important and important
things such as oh that what you just
described not really recognizing the
importance of it
so if if anger has risen
instead of um
seeing that as a result of
me previously not reflecting enough i i
see it because of this content because
someone said this or something
and therefore
yeah you'll blame it on things yeah i'm
not i'm not seeing like my
responsibility and
and
and also by blaming the things you'll
see that's the problem but it's not
really that's the symptom of the problem
what is the problem the problem is that
the mind has not been established enough
that might motivate me in the future to
become established to continue to make
effort to reflect on these themes to
develop this that's what i keep saying
like you need to start recognizing that
liability to anger or to last is already
oh okay so the fact that i'm liable
the fact that those things could arise
means the problem is still there means
the mind is still liable to those things
which means mind has not been directed
in the right context far enough
because i i wouldn't have necessarily
thought that
if i was becoming angry is because of
that person i would have blamed myself i
didn't let go of the anger fast enough i
wasn't concentrated hard enough yeah the
moment in between my concentration
slipped me next time i'll try harder
yeah no that's exactly that's what most
people like again most of them
vast majority has genuine intention in
practice but as i said there's been so
much since the sutas since the buddha's
since the sutas since the buddha's
passing away that
today's work is actually on the level of
uncovering most of the stuff that's been
covered with wrong instructions and
wrong ideas not because somebody
intentionally planned them it's just
that's again if if your baseline is to
over attend things not know what the
answer is not understand means even when
you attend to dhamma you'll do so
wrongly so people generally think that i
need to practice concentration
and absorb myself in moment to moment
and not have anything slip my attention
so that then
disturbing things will not disturb them
so i get disturbed when i
have an oversight basically when when i
slip when i forget about what i was
supposed to look
but that's not what i said to say
you get disturbed when there is greed
aversion delusion
are greed aversion delusion on the level
of objects of your senses and
concentrations and sensations no they're
on the level of your intention on the
level of your state of mind
on the level of your desires and themes
and preconceived notions
so that's where you need to approve them
so that's where all this directing the
mind is yeah yes indirectly directly in
the mind yeah exactly yeah
like basically building like certain
encouragements that will make the mind
sort of go there and that's why one has
to recognize recognize
as you said science science of the mind
and the moods yeah and the better it is
recognizing the signs of the mind it's
basically this recognizing that the mind
is not something
that can be an object of your attention
doesn't matter how hard you focus to the
milliseconds of your experience mind is
not there it's in the opposite direction
and then recognizing that the way
to deal with the mind with such mind
with the mind of such nature
that cannot be directly accessed or
attended is is
is is
well first to refrain from trying to
directly access and attend it and then
recognize that your work is on the level
of building a wider context that your
mind will have to be within
so even and you can start doing that
even before you start seeing your mind
you know you get the intellectual
understanding and then you start certain
recollections reflections evaluations
uh
dwelling on values and benefits and
drawbacks just day-in day-out just
you might approach it through different
themes but you're doing the same
recollection practice it's on the base
of your virtual sensor strain and
solitude your mind will then become visible
your mind will then become visible
you will start seeing this background
leaning towards this or towards that
and those are the signs and features of
the mind that's how you know the mind is
there oh footprints
he must have passed through here
and that's how you find it
so
the somali described here now you could
see how it's just
part of the same development
so because many people would recognize
the value because you can't deny that's
all they should talk about
the value of you know recollecting
re-evaluating thinking right themes and
frequently pondering upon
but then they would still think that the
place for concentration
is is sort of there is a place for
concentration as a separate practice to
this that
helps one another it doesn't
you can only concentrate at the expense
of a context
so you want to practice ahmadi
samadhi as the suit to say is just
composing and steading down and
fortifying your recollectedness
your mindfulness
so your themes your recollections your
frequently thinking and pondering
do that now
even more organized manner
like go under a root of a tree in a
closed room and think and ponder even
longer even more persistently and that is your
even more persistently and that is your
samadhi practice
so
it wouldn't be surprising then
that the result of that would be the first
the result of that would be the first
jhana
which is defined by thinking and
pondering free from greed aversion
delusion free from hindrances
[Music] so how do you free your thinking and
so how do you free your thinking and
pondering from the parasites of greed
aversion delusion well by thinking and
pondering rightly they will take it away
that will purify it like you purify the
gold by directing the mind away from
this exactly by slowly taking it away
and removing the impurities in that
sense but i think as long as one does not
but i think as long as one does not
recognize as you described earlier that
there is this
peripheral there are this peripheral phenomena so
there are this peripheral phenomena so
to say yeah then the latter would
kind of make sense well yes because
because there is nothing else yeah so
try to accept
then rather than catch every moment yeah
you can learn
intellectually first
that catching the moment is taking you
the wrong way and recognize it for
yourself so you start refraining from it
and now that you know you're not
supposed to be doing it that's sort of
step forward
but yes everything you do from the
baseline of
where your attention is which is over
attention let's say like that everything
you do will be overly attended
everything you do will be made an object
of your attention that's why the mind is
invisible but
but
if your views change
and you don't think you should be
attending to things like that anymore
well now you have a chance actually to
discern the middle ground
but if your views don't change
then you're just going to be sort of
creating a patchwork of trying to
include everything that you find helpful
and so on
you know while at the same time ignoring
the bigger picture which is the fact
that well
the suitors don't talk about it
certainly not in the way
commonly approached
and composure is the result of the right
composure is the result of the right
mindfulness
that's the result of the right view the
right view right mindfulness
uh right intention means
right composure because those are the
things that you compose the seven
enlightenment factors goes the first one
is right my opponent is mindfulness and
then it's um
reflecting on dharma like
yeah but seven enlightenment factors
apply to somebody who is at least
thought upon right you need to have a
right view for for any of them
and how would you describe within this
context the practice the practical
way of guarding the sense doors
same uh not losing the sight of
where the problem is so practically
speaking right here right now
do you guard
your eyes
now by focusing on
by focusing on
lumps in your head and feeling
sensations and abdomen
or do you guard your eyes not by
thinking about your eyes but by thinking
about a parallel of things that you
shouldn't look at
feeling that danger peripherally not
where your eyes are
because see if i focus on my eyes i'll
do so at the expense of the context of
what i shouldn't be looking at
so you guard your sense those by
thinking rightly
as to what you should
allow your eyes to look and what you
shouldn't and it is when you forget the danger
and it is when you forget the danger
of looking at the unwholesome things
that's when you intentionally choose to
look that's when you allow those those wild
that's when you allow those those wild
animals of your eyes to go and look
so you guard your eyes now
by basically being mindful of pretty
much your situation as a whole that in
case something
unsuitable for your eyes comes
from some direction you don't look at it
and if you look at it you don't grasp
pleasing signs and features
so it's everywhere but
where the concentration in your eye is
or on your sides
sites yeah the objects of your eyes
because you cannot just look down i just
look at this carpet i just look at this
carpet even that is defined by the actual
even that is defined by the actual
context of why are you doing it
but do you think that just looking down
here will make the problems go away
no
the risk of looking and unwholesome the
risk of being infected by
unwholesome infected by lust aversion and delusion
infected by lust aversion and delusion
that's not in what you see
that's on the level of sense basis the
level of that background the context
stuff you cannot directly attend to also
implied in word guarding it's not an
active exactly guarding does not mean tackling
exactly guarding does not mean tackling
down every single no just means protect
the doorway
all you need to do is make sure the
handle is locked and door is is bad
that's how you guard it
not opening the door and then punching
everybody that tries to come in so
so
and again virtue guarding of the sense
those leads to samadhi if it's done rightly
leads to samadhi if it's done rightly
because what else is guarding of my
senses other than established context
that now defines my values or where will
i let my eyes ears and other senses go
so something seemingly so simple like oh
recollecting the buddha dharma the
sangha the virtue yeah yes fine
that is the basis for somebody
for a lay person and then if you know if
your precepts are upgraded up to eight
precepts and so on
it can on its own
result in ghana and thinking and
pondering that's free from great version
illusion if you spend days months who
knows how long
of cultivating these right moods that
become imperturbable towards greed
aversion and delusion and distraction
then all you need to do is just because
again you did the work
you have cultivated it the animal has
traveled the mind has gone in the right
direction for a long time
now all you need to do is just stay
there just stay in that secluded environment
just stay in that secluded environment
be moderate in eating and this context
will be fueled by those right things
and same like with with brahma biharas
the lamin khan
it's the establishment of the context of
friendliness non-ill will
but it's not a technique that will
result in this experience of it no it's
something you have to frequently reflect
upon for yourself for others in every
for yourself for others in every
direction up and down doesn't matter
until no path
has been left
unreflected to put it away
to put it away
and if you frequently think and ponder
about it the mind will incline towards
friendliness whether you want it or not
and the mind has been inclining and
traveling in the direction of
friendliness long enough
even meeting unfriendly people will not
perturb you or certainly not as much as
before yes and that's completely different from
yes and that's completely different from
when someone is someone i meet is
disagreeable or is and then i do matter
exactly yeah yeah counter it anti-node
yes hatred is mad do it why
not because you're really friendly just
because you want to get rid of this
comfort of witnessing unfriendly person
so you're reverse to what you're feeling
and back until i said most people's
practice comes down to being a verse
towards their own states of mind trying
to get rid of them so all you can do
when it arises is just endure it because
anything you do
will be trying to get rid of it
otherwise when the unpleasant well all you can do
when the unpleasant well all you can do
is yeah like endure it in a sense of
don't act towards it but see now we just
define what you can do
carry on evaluating re-evaluating
thinking about buddha dhamma sangha
virtue and friendliness
with your motivation to get rid of you
can you can but uh it won't last though
because it's not directly dealing with
what's bothering you see it already
implies recognition that
what i'm trying to get rid of
is not actually the problem the problem
is the mind hasn't traveled far enough
in the right direction
so it can be a motive a motivator
to to reflect and even if you initially
do it to get rid of it again the
direction of getting rid of it is
opposite of evaluating reevaluating
recollecting rightly so in other words
you won't be able to do it for those
reasons much longer
if it's authentic
yeah yeah provided you already see that
relationship between you and your own
mind which is what chittenden imitates
yeah if you see it as as a thing that's there
if you see it as as a thing that's there
that inclines the hair or there
depending on what you keep providing in
in allowing it to feed on
that should be the initial stage of
trying to get rid of craving by craving
exactly yeah yeah so yeah there's
craving involved but see now
it's not actually fueling more cravings
because you're not acting out of their
version you're acting okay yeah fine i want to
you're acting okay yeah fine i want to
get rid of this it's unpleasant yeah i
want to abandon it
do i abandon it by cultivating moral
will towards it no i abandon it by
making my context
even less betterable
up until it becomes imperturbable and
even more important
and there you go you abandoned it
there you go you abandoned it
they need to deal with it exactly the
pressure not um being affected by it
yeah and that's how you go beyond the
and that's how you go beyond the
hindrances as well
they're the symptoms of where your mind
is
so you go beyond them
what by enduring them and by cultivating
the context that cannot be perturbed by
those hindrances and then they cease to
well they cease to hinder you as i said
so many times
so then it's just agreeable disagreeable
and everything else in between but none
of that
can overpower overwhelm and limit your
mind so that's often why somebody then is
so that's often why somebody then is
referred to as
uh
boundless unconstricted
unconstricted
nothing mystical about it
if your
wholesome mood on account of right
recollection in the buddha dhamma sangha
it's been cultivated for years actively
on account of your virtue and sense
restraint there's going to be some pretty
there's going to be some pretty
unshakeable samadhi pretty unconstrained
no worldly constraints can sort of limit
it and bring it down that mood
on account of that mood you will be
factually joyful happy with a calm body and
joyful happy with a calm body and
content
because it's a good mood
yeah you cannot take offense anymore
because taking involves sort of leaping
out into that thing which is offending
you you're moving in the opposite
direction yeah
in other words the
the attempt to take it if the mother
presents it
is within the good mood in other words
good mood can handle even the attempt to
take it without fearing it you're not
trying to get rid of it or prevent it
it's included within it
so it occurred to me that from a mundane
point of view somebody might be sitting
in an office having to write a very
difficult email
and they might say to their colleagues i
want to concentrate on writing this
difficult email but whatever actually
ends up doing is closing the door to the
office so that they can be alone
and then they and then they recollect
the importance of sending this email
properly being aware of the consequences
if they do it wrongly but they might
assume that this is
concentration called like that
but what they actually do is much closer
to what we have been discussing as
somali right context
right context
in order to do something properly
exactly then i might go to a meditation
retweet and learn how to concentrate
which is actually leading them away from
what they were strangely already doing
more closer to the actual somalia except
they just call it concentration and
might not have understood that this is
what they're practically doing 100
that's exactly what it is because that's
what i said before even when people are
concentrating and watching their
sensations there is a certain context to that you
there is a certain context to that you
have certain motivation intentions while
you are doing it so
but then you become unaware of it
because you're doubling down onto the
concentration aspect
so all you need to do
is again become aware of the motivation
behind your actions which is carried my
current action is concentration
why what is the theme what is the context
what is the theme what is the context
for me practicing this concentration
technique that i find helpful
what is the theme
what is my motivation why am i doing
this because i want to get rid of the pain
because i want to get rid of the pain
okay
that's the first step
how do you go about it where is the pain
take that reflection further and you
will stop concentrating and you will
start practicing samadhi more rightly
because when the buddha described
a skilled monk
practicing samadhi towards liberation
you know either walking up and down or
sitting cross-legged
it wasn't through concentration it was
through constant reviewing on his mind
about unwholesome states that are
present or could be present wholesome
states that are present and could be
present and then encouraging one and
discouraging other
setting up directions reflections
evaluations so that his mind travels
away from a wholesome day in there
purifying it purifying it purifying and
then checking if it's pure and then
purify and then checking if it's pure
and that's exactly where the work is so
would you say writing about the dharma
can also be useful and then
going back to one's writing and then
it depends yeah i think initially if you
write what you have acutely
established as a context yes
but if you start writing on its own that
will take too much of your concentration
it will become it will require too much
of attention how you're going to become
concentrated on that and actually forget
your situation here and now yeah yeah
and that same like with a scholastic
study or pretty much almost always
results in that yeah yeah but
but
in a sense
it can be
useful to evoke the same theme if um
well i found
so for example
it might just be
maybe five sentences or something that that
five sentences or something that that
i'll write to see if i've understood
something oh yeah yeah no that that's a
useful practice we established there
before and then and then i'll come back
to it
the next day and see oh actually
isn't it could be much clearer and then
i'll come back and say oh yeah and then
i find in the week that it's turned into
something much clearer or yeah because no that's
much clearer or yeah because no that's
you wouldn't be doing any of that at the
expense of your context exactly you're
really just trying to
to crystallize it further so it's then
easier to sustain it and think about it
in even further terms and it's not to
impress some academic or no no
you're not writing it within the
constraints of academic paper with how
it has to be written no no it's just
just conveying what you're thinking
right there and then yeah it doesn't
make sense
yeah does it make sense exactly
it makes sense to me but
can i describe it can i put it in words
this context this recollection these
values that i'm thinking about that that are
that i'm thinking about that that are
sort of influencing my moods and so on
can i
define that can i clarify it and then
exactly if you come back to later you
realize oh there is more to it now that
i haven't mentioned before or just that
oh that wasn't that profound or exactly
i was like maybe it wasn't as good as
you thought it was yeah when you tried
to put it in words it doesn't really
make sense it's like okay well did it
make sense in my mind or you just felt
good exactly yeah sometimes you write
something and because you're in a good
mood you're elated or something yeah you
think it's so profound yeah and then you
come back to and you realize yeah that
was just because i i was in a pleasure
so you you don't wanna
like again good mood and so on
it will follow but you don't want to put
the emphasis on that exactly the
emphasis on that clarity
where the work of
reevaluating and recollecting is
and good mood will follow and when the
good mood goes away it doesn't matter
the the threat of your understanding it
remains unchanged
by the badminton
and then of course eventually the the
bad mood
will be a good move
as the buddha says like you abandon
them the the
pain
and suff pain and suffering of a
household life
you you're abandoning by replacing it
with pains and suffering of a renunciate
life so the bad mood of an established mind
so the bad mood of an established mind
it's it's better than a good mood of a
lay life and non-established mind
and you will know that so it's like oh
yeah it's just
agreeable disagreeable as they would
have said you know he would have
teach somebody dhamma they ignore him he
says that's disagreeable to him but that
that's disagreeable to him but that
doesn't overwhelm his mind
but even the yeah generally the
yeah the bad mood or the sort of
disagreeable feelings pertaining to the
renunciate life are superior to even the
good mood of the of the non-renancial
life yeah yeah exactly exactly
i think it's it just reminds me the
blame or criticism from the wise is
superior to the praise of fools and oh
yeah sure
so fundamental good mood
is the mood when there is no emotion
felt hmm
as sadopoutou said the fact that
nothing's felt that's what's pleasant
in a mind that's that's awakened
so the pleasure of no mood
means the pleasure of of uh
no possibility
to be disturbed
it reminded me when you said about the
like use of the word footprints of the
of the mind kind of the signs of this
it kind of reminded me of a
sort of a
analogy that
had occurred to me um
just or yeah similarly in regard to the
because people you usually assume when
you're um
about about mindfulness of breathing the
kind of general idea is that it's very
you know pleasant and calming and
everything but actually
but actually
it kind of occurred to me that's not
it's not um
i've often
experienced it as being like being
mindful of the breath
is not it wasn't really pleasant or it
wasn't necessarily pleasant it was kind
of like
because the analogy that occurred to me
it's kind of like um
feeling or recognizing that there's a
kind of a enemy
stock kind of active the word stalking
you on your tail waiting to kill you
really as in is this all but he's kind
of always there in the background behind
you footprint of his the things that is
sort of his he leaves his trail
and it's it's a yeah i was just i was
actually gonna play yeah that was one of
the things
i thought about yesterday to mention
today but obviously kind of went in a
different direction was that actually
yeah anapanasati done rightly
most likely will not be pleasant first
yeah it's it's not going to be unpleasant in
it's it's not going to be unpleasant in
a sense of so painful no but it's going
to be like a like a certain dissonance
let's say like that
like certain
kind of at odds
and it's exactly that
that which is breathing
it's it's it's a perpetual
misstep with what you think you are and
your sense of control over it yeah
cultivate that misstep and you will
abandon your sense of control and what
you are
obviously if you have the right view but
you're not going to be able to see that
that murderer that's talking you so to
speak that danger or that that body without
that danger or that that body without
having
that certain amount of composure that
knowledge and vision of the way things
are yeah without having the right view
you can't have it without that composure
yeah as well you know without that
composure being to a certain level then
you take on underpants it's like that um
similarly of that bowl with water
filled with water whichever way it tips
it just
you can everything will go that way so
it's like you build up that composure
and now i take on a panasonic
and what gets revealed yeah these things
these things and that which you build up
is yeah it's the right view the right
composure the right recollection all of
that and then
when when at least right view is established
when at least right view is established
cultivating anapanasati
is sort of uh
revealing and fortifying that misstep
whereby you will cease to assume
your side of the step first
and the
breathing body second and start seeing
the breathing body as the first and you
a second
so breathing doing anapanasati rightly
it's like a simultaneous undermining of
your sense of control while you're
breathing it breathing out yes exactly
and that misstep it's it's that like
subtle dissonance that's not pleasant
yeah but again if you know the signs and
features you recognize oh it's that
misstep that calms everything else down
because all the disturbances don't come
from things don't come from body don't
come from breathing in or breathing in
breathing in out like this or in like
that they come from my gratuitous sense
of ownership gratuitous conceit
greed aversion delusion that's where
they come from and misstep
basically neutralizes them
you just cannot they cannot
fester and grow and live and persist in
that environment so frequently practice
anapanasati in the misstep of
anapanasati the mischief of unownable breeding while
the mischief of unownable breeding while
you're breathing
and your sense of control will fade it
will win away it has to
until there are no traces over left and
the misstep is the how things always
work
now you're just not trying to pervert it
through your assumption and negligence
which is then no longer seen as a
misstep exactly put in the first the
second the second is first is defined by
what you thought should be the first or
second on its own it was always there as
first